All right. Hello, welcome. It's August
19th, 2025.
We're in active stream guest stream
117.1
with Robert Stamps who will be
presenting on control strategies and
predictive coding using magnetic noise.
Thank you for joining Robert and looking
forward to this presentation and then
discussion with and close.
>> Close the YouTube on your side, Robert.
Okay.
Do Oh, should I just begin now?
Okay. Yes. Um All right. All right.
Well, well, thank you for this
invitation. Uh it's uh maybe I should
give you a little bit of a background of
how I ended up uh doing this research
getting interested into this problem
because I I'm primarily a condensed
matter physicist in computational and
theory primarily
um and my area of specialization has
been in magnetic materials and spin
systems in general but I've been doing
this for quite a while
and about I would guess 25 years ago I
was more or less starting my career. I
was in Australia at the time and
I also had came across a paper uh it was
about the theory of flocking and I found
that very interesting and that led to
one thing and led to another thing and
eventually I found myself co-supervising
a PhD student who was working with uh an
expert in uh psychology on psychopysics
and there was looking experiments and
analyzing experiments on uh primate
visual systems
And what I found striking was some of
the mathematics we were doing. We were
heavily influenced by uh I think about
that time in fact just recently a Row
and Ballard paper had come out and it
was heavily influenced by the the
structural form of the mathematics we
were doing and it mapped directly back
on to some of the things I was thinking
about doing uh with magnetic systems at
that time. people were just starting to
develop a fabrication technique which
would allow them to uh make new kinds of
magnetic materials and that's what I'm
going to discuss today and it occurred
to me at that time I remember very
clearly that when that technology
matured it seemed to me like it would be
an ideal one to try and implement some
sort of neuromorphic
uh designs in and indeed that is exactly
what has panned out and so I'll tell you
a little bit about that and what the
state of the field is now and and that's
but that explains more or less how I I
began my interest in this kind of
cross-disciplinary
field and just to put the story back
into context and about 3 years ago I had
a sbatical I decided to go back to
Australia and visit that group and see
what had happened and that's when I came
across Friston's papers and active
inference and uh uh I actually didn't
make header tale of them and so I
thought well I better put it into some
context I can understand and to try and
understand exactly what what predictive
coding and active inference are about
and that helped me and that's where this
work emerged from trying to understand
that so let me let me begin then so I'll
just explain these pictures
this is just a schematic of using
nanomagnets with an active inference to
control some process and then your
feedback and this is a schematic of the
sort of nano particle arrays which are
in this control box. Uh this is my
idealized spin system and what this is
at the very end I could show you it's
it's a a model which is a bit more
sophisticated but it actually tries to
model properly the properties of real
magnetic materials and the point of it
was to demonstrate that ywin could
implement certain algorithms inside a
magnetic context like this.
So
to begin, let me introduce myself. Uh
the people I work with here
uh focus primarily on studying both
theoretically and experimentally
nanomagnets. The experimental parts are
led by my colleague, Professor Lup
Bonerup. And these are students who
involved one way or another in some of
the the works. Some of it overlaps with
what I'm going to show you today. And
these are just illustrations of some of
the different systems which other people
and which we also have have looked at
over the years. Uh these each of these
represent a little magnet. But before I
explain all of that, let me give you a
little bit of an outline. Um this is a
just an inspiration. It's a wonderful
beautiful picture of a fly larvae. And
you can see all the neurons here are are
close packed and they expand out as as
the the fly uh as it grows into a fly.
But the efficiency and the minimal
amount of of connections and yet what
the fly can do is is really quite
amazing. And that's a little bit of what
trying to discover in all of this. So
for the first thing first thing I'll
start with is a little bit introduction
to what I mean by magnetism and
nanomagnets
and why I think this might be a possible
platform at least for some key aspects
of what I think is called predictive
coding and then I'll give some examples
active inference and tracking and some
other examples as well and then finally
when I talked about these real systems
and more sophisticated models to
demonstrate uh material specific
properties then I have some
micromagnetic examples that's what they
call it so let me start with a quick
overview of magnetism and nanomagnets
and some key definitions so I apologize
if you've seen all of this before if it
uh but uh it just gives us a way of
defining terms uh in a in a common way
so what is a nanomagnet
Well, just means it's a little piece of
magnetic material. This is a real
picture. Uh the particles themselves are
smaller than a micrometer. They're maybe
100 200 nanometers in length and half
that size in width. And an example
material would be an iron nickel
compound. And the shape is what matters
here. The shape is such that they tend
to align as all the magnetization
pointing in one direction or the other
direction but always along this axis
that minimizes the energy of the the the
magnetic atoms. Uh so at lower
temperatures then they form this
magnetization and it tends to align
along an axis. So it can be fairly well
controlled just by the shape and the
lithography is has has been developing
steadily over the last 20 years. So one
can even make smaller well- definfined
particles. Now the nice thing about it
by being able to make many of these
particles and place them in close
proximity to one another is that these
little magnets interact with one another
just by stray magnetic fields. It's the
same sort of magnetic fields that holds
a magnet to a a refrigerator door. Uh
but what it does then is depending on
which way the magnet in the magnetic
particle is oriented, it always likes to
be north south. So if I draw little
arrows to represent which direction the
magnetization the particle is, they
always try to order in a way that uh
minimizes the stray field energy uh
which is represented by these little bar
magnets I've drawn schematically over
here. And so to be north south like that
means that they if they're placing in
this direction they like to be
antiparallel that minimizes their
energy. Whereas if you place them at a
corner like this then they'll form a
corner and try to make a chain. uh the
point is there is an energy associated
with their interaction. They can adjust
their orientation to minimize that
energy and that's sort of the basis
starting point for where I think this
overlaps with uh the act the predictive
coding algorithm.
Um so the shape just means they have
arrows along one direction and you can
place them close together and then they
behave like little toy magnets.
Now the freedom and flexibility of the
lithography which has developed over the
years is you can place them in all sorts
of interesting geometries where these
interactions can compete. And the name
of that field is artificial spin ice and
it is motivated by uh a residual entropy
that was predicted by poly for water
ice. the way that the um uh polarization
the the distribution between plus and
minus charges would order just in
regular water ice. It is frustrated. It
competes. It cannot find its minimum
minimum energy. And one can engineer
that and study the frustration by
putting these particles in certain
arrangements. So this arrangement uh is
one where there's a two-fold degenerate
ground state and it forms net
anti-feromagnet meaning there's a
cancellation of all the magnetic
moments. This one where you just rotate
everything a little bit prefers a
ferroagnetic orientation. So there's a
net magnetic moment. Others which can be
engineered uh are are not really in
either of these classes. They they are
instead what they're called topological
ordering.
So I'm going to talk about primarily
this ferromagnet one just to illustrate
the key ideas here. Before I do that,
uh, as I was telling you before my
interest in this area, I I was thinking
that someday people are going to develop
these magnetic arrays once I have the
technology uh, for neuromorphic
application. And indeed that has been
seen in the last 5 years where there are
primarily reservoir computing algorithms
have been implemented and one of the
motivations in fact the prime motivation
for this is the power efficiency. So if
we think about a conventional
semiconductor-based logic, a computer,
the information is moved around by
charge currents and charge currents lose
energy through dual heating through
resistance. So all the heat that's
generated by the CPU uh is just wasted
energy from moving charges around. Uh
information in a magnetic system can be
encoded in the direction of little
arrows I just talked about. The energy
involved in reversing these little
arrows can be in fact as as as small as
is allowed thermodynamically in
principle. It's called the land hour
limit. And this is not just a factor of
two or three more efficient. It is
orders of magnitude more efficient than
uh what can be done by moving charges
around. So that is one of the prime
motivations for trying to implement some
of the very computationally heavy
activities associated with uh machine
learning. Um and that's motivated this
field. There's some other things too.
You you can start thinking about
modifying individual elements and states
next uh horizon is actually being able
to do this in three dimensions and
people are making strides toward that.
So it's an interesting area and it has
the promise or at least the potential of
uh introducing a non semiconductor and
conventional platform which is
particularly power efficient for
conventional and non-conventional
computing.
So
to make use of all that there's some
basic concepts. So I'll begin with this
design here of a spin system. Now it
prefers to align at in its lowest energy
configuration such that there is if you
add up the little arrows there will be a
net magnetic moment meaning there'll be
a net number of arrows which don't
cancel out. These cancel out in that
direction but this group of four those
add. And there's four different ways to
do that. It could be these two adding
and these cancelling. And what we care
about is the average direction of the
arrow which is the average
magnetization. So I define a
magnetization then as an average and it
will be a thermal average and where
these little sigas represent the
individual spins making up the
magnetization.
And this can be averaged over the entire
material. And so if you do that, you
would measure then the average
magnetization
the way these superimpose with one
another. So that you have a
magnetization curve which would look uh
as a function of temperature. Uh they
all for a ferroagnet like to lie in the
same direction or nearly lie as you
increase temperature. But at some
critical temperature uh spins will start
reversing and point in another direction
and that reduces the magnetization.
And the rate at which this happens we
call a susceptibility
and statistically that's actually a
correlation function. Those two things
are important because those are the two
things which I will try to uh convince
you overlap directly into a predictive
coding scheme and just enable it. then
the magnetization to act as a platform
for implementing this sort of thing. So
the next bit that's important is to
recognize how the magnetization
evolves over time the processes
involved. So if I consider a whole lot
of these little magnets, whatever
geometry it is in, I can adjust the
orientation with a magnetic field which
I might apply externally. So I might
generate a magnetic field either through
another magnet or a coil or something
like that and apply it to this array and
that if it's strong enough it will tend
to align all the magnetizations as much
as they can uh in the direction of that
field. Now if I reduce that field and I
have a finite temperature there'll be a
reduction in the number of uh spins or
elements which like to point in their
original direction and some of them will
start to favor alignment with the field
in its new direction and so there might
be a region which is pointed oppositely
the others. So you see there's a net
reduction in the magnetization. And as I
increase the magnetic field in this new
direction, this region grows at the
expense of the other region until when I
get to a large enough field, everything
is pointing in the opposite direction.
Um the point I want to make here is this
is all happening in time and it can be
observed in real time. So here's an
example of an experiment that was done
on on such a system where they start the
magnetization in one direction, then
apply a small field to give it another
direction and then watch what happens as
it evolves. And so microscopically what
happens is all the spins were oriented
one way and then one starts to reverse
that causes or makes it more probable
that another spin nearby will reverse
which makes it more probable that yet
another spin will reverse until they all
reverse. This all happens in real time
and there's a statistical probability of
each of these reversals. So that time
that it occurs in always changes a
little bit but it is a stochastic
process and each reversal is sampling
the configuration space but it's always
looking for a way to minimize its
energy. So it's always trying to relax
into a lowest energy configuration.
So that sets me now to where I can talk
about the overlap with predictive
coding. Um,
everybody here I think knows much more
about this than I. Uh, I've been
struggling to understand the logic
behind it, but I think I've got a a
better idea now. Um,
if we think about two variables
associated, well, I I think of it this
way. If I'm looking at the visual
system, which I'm a little bit more
familiar with, and I I throw an object
in the air, my eyes are following it.
Uh, but they're they're doing it in a
semi-random way. Okay, there's psychic
eye motion and they're there tend to to
where am I going to look in the next
instant is going to depend on what I've
perceived in the previous instance. And
so there's a lot of information there.
There's velocity, position, all of that.
But I'm going to to look in an area
where it's probably more probable to
find the object in the next instant. So
there's two things going on. I have a
perception and I have some expectation
or belief of where it's and what I'm
interested in or what my neurons are
interested in is a probability
distribution relating these two
quantities
now and and that's where the the whole
theory begins. So I've got some sort of
input data and I've got some sort of
belief state of my neurons and I'm going
to say there's some sort of mapping and
it it's not a perfect one to one. It's
it's stochastic. there's a certain
randomness
uh on on both both sides of this and
I'll say that that non there's a
nonlinear function mapping it or it can
be nonlinear uh mapping uh say my
perception to a belief with bit of
random noise as well or maybe my next
belief the transition to my next belief
is also going to be a nonlinear mapping
or linear it can be linearized as well
but it's some sort of mapping some
function I don't necessarily know what
that function is and moreover this can
be in a hierarchical system. So like the
the original Ral Ballard paper where a
lot of this uh was was uh described in
terms of vision is a layered system uh
where there's an image input from the
the back of the eye and then that feeds
forward into regions of the brain. there
feed forward uh differences between the
expectation what was perceived and then
a prediction of which way maybe the eye
ought to move next uh or it would
involve that and you keep going up the
ladder and back and forth.
But I think that the main idea is that
each layer tries to minimize locally uh
its error function and match up the
predictions with the perceptions at each
layer. And so this this is a little bit
different I think than a lot of of uh
global oriented machine learning
algorithms that are maybe a bit more uh
uh familiar with. Um, one other thing
too when I gave my example about
tracking an object, there's a lot of
information being gathered in each time
interval and that includes position, but
it also includes velocity and
accelerations can in principle be any
order of dynamics. And so in addition to
having a hierarchical uh u layering uh
one can also envision a kind of a
lateral hierarchy if you want. And so I
call that dynamic ordering. And that
that is I think the idea that that
Friston uh introduced uh back in the in
the the late two around 2008 and so on.
And
what the idea that evolves from all of
that is I now have new indices that
complicate my my states and my
perceptions. They're indexed by by layer
and by dynamic order. But the time
evolution of my beliefs then with this
dynamic information also introduce a
term over here. But they're governed
primarily uh by this uh relaxation of
some energy function. And that tends to
to to uh uh that's the free energy idea
that you're trying to to find an extreal
value. And it's this gradient which is
most interesting for me uh for for what
guides this because that's where I can
map that onto the magnetic system most
easily. And I put a little note here
that this is a langean type equation but
it can be also derived in in the physics
context where most physicists would be
familiar with the fauler plank equation
for the distribution the time evolution
of a joint distribution function and
these equations emerge naturally from
that.
Um here's how we do it with predictive
coding then in magnetization. So, I've
got my my state variables. Uh, you might
call them the hidden states and the more
visible states. They're indexed by layer
in the hierarchy, but also by dynamic
order. And I'm going to say that I'm
going to translate this statement of a a
nonlinear mapping between the visible
and hidden states through these G and F
functions. I'm going to translate them
into measurements
on a magnetic system. And the magnetic
system uh is uh a magnetization
something which responds where I put a
field on it. That field is a function of
these variables these state variables
and the magnetization is what responds
or how the system responds to that
magnetization. As I said earlier, system
is always trying to find a way to
minimize its mechanical energy and its
entropy, maximize its entropy uh subject
to whatever that constraining field is.
So if I can sample that, that's why I
put these angular brackets. It's a
stochastic sampling.
uh then I get a measure of the system
trying to relax as it it must
uh to uh a more energetically favorable
configuration and I just in interpret
that relaxation as an instantaneous
value of the visible and hidden states.
So this is all done at some finite
temperature T. And the trick then is to
figure out what this field is and then
make a measurement of the magnetization.
And so my lang equation then with this
gradient of this error term or energy
translates into a transition rate for my
state variables here. the belief uh
subject to this term which is
effectively a force guiding the
magnetization toward a lower energy
state.
So the terms that appear just for some
details in how the mapping occurs the
field which is the all important thing
that's acting on the magnetization is a
gradient of some energy function and
that energy function is the lowest order
expression for that is the difference
between this nonlinear mapping and the
average of my state whether I'm at
whatever layer I'm in and at whatever
order I'm in. And that defines my
effective field. The terms which appear
then there's a some parameter a
precision uh which in my magnetic system
goes like an inverse temperature and
magnetization which is my f function and
the derivative of that f function which
is my susceptibility. So all these two
things I can get from a measurement. uh
I do it computationally but they be can
be done through measurements. Uh we do
that for data recording for example
magnetic data recording all the time and
this is the quantity then that tells me
how my state variables will evolve in
time.
So the algorithm is really actually
quite simple. At each time step, I
sample my magnetization on some magnetic
array where I've subjected it to a field
which is a function of whatever the
previous values for the state variables
were. Then having measured that
magnetization, I get new values for my
state variables and I calculate fields
and I repeat the process.
So it's nothing more than that. It's the
same thing we used to do with magnetic
recording. Still do do with magnetic
recording. You have information on a
magnetic material. Uh you read it, but
you can also write it. You just repeat
it. So it's it's really quite simple and
it's an old fairly wellestablished
technology.
What's different is doing it on uh sort
of micrometer size patterns. Well,
that's not different either. Um, here's
an example. So, here's a three layer
network with three dynamic nodes who
would correspond to three different
magnetic arrays.
And I would apply a field separately to
each one of these arrays in my updates.
And then I just make a measurement of
the magnetization from each of these
nine arrays, feed it back in to get nine
more fields, and just keep iterating.
That's my implementation of the
longitude equations that govern the uh
predictive coding and that's how it
works. Um it really is kind of simple.
Here's an example. So I've done one uh
which is fairly recent actually. Uh it
it's not dynamic. It's just the
layering. I modeled it on the RA Ballard
paper. So it's but it's it's a simple
one-dimensional version. So I I have uh
an image with one dimension. It's just a
sinosoid. So I got a feature in it. Um
then I uh and I and I don't have very
many nodes. I think this was like 30 or
something like that. And then I uh
reduce it to my first active layer uh
mu1 which uh I think had something like
18 nodes. And then I reduce it down to
six nodes in mu2. and a bit more feature
extraction with mu3. And then for mu3
uh I can do a reconstruction. Now over
here mu1 and mu3 don't look very good.
That's because I'm doing it at high
temperature. My original image looks
like that and the reconstruction looks
like that. When I lower the temperature
because remember you know I get a
critical point where the magnetization
disappears. When I lower the temperature
well quite a different picture. Here's
my input data. Here's my first layer.
It's learned it pretty well. Uh here's
the second layer which is extracting
some features learned from this and more
refinement at this layer. Then I
reconstruct from this layer the full
image and it matches pretty well. But
that's at low temperature. So this just
illustrates I think where the magnetic
uh system you you can actually see what
it it is actually doing something. uh
and it's through this nonlinear
function.
Another example
uh this is now one which includes the
dynamics. So it's a tracking example and
I was inspired there was a a thesis
written by uh millillage I think it is
it's quite nice thesis
uh and uh in his chapter 3 he did
something like this I thought that was
quite nice so I implemented it here
and uh this is a sinosoid and I I give
into it because I've got three dynamic
orders as well as three hierarchical
orders so I have a velocity and
acceleration and an acceleration the
acceleration
um and that input data then is
represented here with my fi and then
this is the layer one um and it
following the sinosoid quite nicely this
is the layer two uh which is using a
visible layer from here I'm by the way
I'm I'm following a paper the formalism
I'm using is is uh by buckley uh So have
that hierarchy that they've used. So
this is their visible and their hidden
notation. These are errors on that and
it's following quite nicely. So then was
curious how this what's being learned if
anything. So I tried a non-periodic
input. Um so I would just uh at each
position choose randomly a velocity. So
sometimes go up or down. It's a
one-dimensional example. And you see it
does pretty well following even that
random force choices in velocity. So I
ran it for some time and then I turned
off the signal. So I turned off my input
here. And as you can see the hidden
states however they keep going on. Looks
like they they learned a trajectory from
the most recent steps. Uh and so it is
appears that they it did learn to
predict which way the system was going
to go. And yet you can see here it makes
very quick corrections. But here there's
no input data and it will eventually
come back down to that. Um and this is
going a lot of stuff is being filtered
at the higher lay layers. They respond a
bit more quickly than the lowest layer.
And that's all consistent too with uh
the observations that different time
scales are happening at different
hierarchical layers.
um
active inference which I haven't done
yet but it's here uh this is this
example so it's what I showed you on the
very first slide nanomagnet control
feedback to a process and then
information coming back to the
nanomagnets and again this is just
repeating what was done in the Buckley
paper uh the active inference part is
this a so we have the we've associated
then some change in the process
uh which appears then as a new function
in this e function and this appears in
the in the in the perception part. So I
look at how that is changing and adjust
whatever this a signal is based on what
is believed by the nanomagnets
and the target here is a linearized f
function but I'm still using uh an
average over that linear f function uh
of a of from my simulating it with my
thermal magnets. So introduced into that
function is a target value TD. And what
that means is the system is going to try
and align its perceptions through A with
its belief that it ought to be at a
temperature TD. And this function uh
that is going on in the process is
unknown to the system. Uh so it has to
it can't know the function. and it just
has to adjust uh its position with mu in
such a way as to get the data coming
back into the nanomagnet to give it a
value of TD. So this target here is the
green line and here is the measurement
is the orange and the belief is the blue
and you see it starts off over here far
away from the target and then it
oscillates and exponentially decays down
uh until it hits the target.
And this is the other bit of information
that's coming in. That's that's the
temperature. This is the rate of bit
change of the temperature with respect
to to whatever this this value uh x is
that it's sending to a and uh so it's
got these two bits of input which is
just the position and and the velocity
whoops went backwards and then this is
the error function and I found it
actually useful to see this as a
trajectory so that if I look at the
belief in blue which is really what my
spins are doing and the perception
that's coming back in uh which is my fi
and they're starting off here and then
the perception is slowly coming around
and oscillating into its target value
here and you see that the blue which is
the stochastic magnets they're
oscillating as well but doing quite a
bit more jumping around but they also
then find their center of gravity at the
target point. Um this is just a note
that rather than doing the simulation, I
can actually uh capture most of what's
going on here with a a simpler
approximation which is is quite common
in in magnetic systems. It's a brilluin
function uh which allows me to introduce
temperature and you see it gives me the
same qualitative features
uh that I had with the actual magnetic
system.
Um this is another thing which is that
system below before was was just for
three dynamical orders in one one layer
one hierarchical layer. Um there are
parameters which matter these precisions
on two sets of terms which appear in my
effective energy. Um I can get rid of
the oscillations by adjusting these
parameters. So what I did was I I
basically built an active inference
acting on the acting inference if you
will. Uh so I built another network uh
again with magnetic spins and uh their
job however was to measure the free the
energy uh the energy cost of the first
layer which is interacting with the
process over time. So they were running
much slower and then try to minimize
that energy by feeding back to these
parameters uh the the lambda z and
lambda omega and so this was the the
first iteration it just got started but
now I collected data and then uh there's
feedback from this active inference
acting on the acting inference which got
a fewer oscillations and as I repeat
this through this learning exercise you
see it gets quite good near the end
after about eight nine repeats and it
just goes smoothly to the target. So,
it's adjusted these parameters uh
relative to the starting point to to
take it exactly to the target without a
lot of searching around.
Um
the last thing I'll mention is this.
We're done with fairly simple models
that is simple spins real magnets that
people can make are not that simple.
Although I did demonstrate you can use a
fairly fairly straightforward mean field
theory uh to get the the essential
behaviors but that's a far cry from
actually making a device. So there are
tools for trying to simulate better more
accurately more realistically magnetic
nano particles. So I applied those tools
and they can be done at finite
temperature. It's just a different
algorithm and it's called micromagnetics
and I can put in parameters which are
measured and known for materials iron
nickel being one one of the compounds
and various iso various variants of
those compounds. But there are things
that people can actually make
lithographically into the kind of
designs which I was showing. Um, so I
chose one with 16 spins
and and in this kind of a geometry. So
it's a much simpler kind of system than
than uh what I showing before. And I did
this tracking exercise, but now call it
a a PID controller. This is what it
would look like electronically. Uh what
I did was the same thing uh except it
would be done with 16 spins and it did
the same sort of targeting uh adjustment
and oscillates around here where I'm now
measuring directly uh the magnetization
through my micromagnetic simulations and
then adjusting those for applied field
which then is feeding back into uh my
imaginary thermostat over here.
uh another application of the 16 spin
system. If I uh say feed in an input
function which is a sinosoid and a
cosine uh for my two dynamical orders um
I can
move the system of my 16 spins such that
from one initial condition to another
which is specifi which I specify will
correspond to an average magnetization.
That average magnetization is nothing
more than uh the average number of spins
pointing to the right or up and down. Uh
and I can pick then a set of states by
picking my starting points and my final
points. I can target a little subset of
states uh where the magnets specific
magnets are pointing in one direction or
the other. So I can pick examples of
this has a certain magnetization, this
has a certain magnetization, this has a
certain magnetization corresponding to
the alignment of the spins. I can choose
those states with some precision just by
picking my initial and final conditions.
Um the final one is just an example that
uh what is a computationally hard
problem in the field which is if you
have a real nano particle some finite
size with a lot of different kinds of
more complex interactions uh how do you
reverse it in a very very short time and
this algorithm works rather nicely. uh
reverses a magnetization from pointing
up here to pointing down there by
applying a pulseed shaped pulsed field
in the right directions moving the field
as well which is a really difficult
problem. Uh you can't can't solve that
very easily using any of the tools that
people have at the moment
and that's it. Um that's my my short
summary. I think maybe nanomagnets and I
think a broad class of systems probably
um provide natural platforms for
predictive coding by making this sort of
mapping onto the magnetization or
whatever the order parameter is and the
susceptibility which are all temperature
dependent. Um they're also stochastic
processes. they are minimizing a
physical degree energy and you can just
map the two on to this apparently and
constrain the system to evolve along a
trajectory which we would recognize then
in an active inference example. Um I'm
also particularly interested in in
systems which uh are complex and like uh
glasses and spin glasses. Some of these
display all sorts of various odd and not
very well understood dynamics and I'm
wondering about whether or not there's
some avenues into those studies by
employing this sort of a of a
methodology if you will. Um that's it.
So
thank you Robert that was awesome.
Anyone watching live, please write any
questions first. The Vladimir, please
feel free to give any opening remarks
and ask any questions you have first.
>> Yeah, this is very interesting. Uh I
just presentations and it I have several
questions for for this. Uh so what your
system what I see that it works and it
can do calculations. what what you say
predictive coding is mostly the doing
computation with the m matter and in
this uh system I think this there's a
main uh part that it it is based on the
mean field yes so that you you are using
lerine equations and this is
going to the you have a um
free energy minimar and So they go to
the minima and uh this system just learn
uh the path and that's what you have
this gradients towards the minimum and
so this is the basis of the system the
why it can be predictable and then how
you can uh calculate
>> yes this is correct
>> yeah yeah that's exactly it that's why I
think it's rather general can be taken
outside of magnetic systems as Well,
>> yeah. Yeah. So, this is quite general.
So, you are at equilibrium. So, you have
several uh local minimar and you can
even make those
changes within the minima. Yes. So, for
example, if you have a system with
several minimar and the kinetic
barriers. So, that's can you also
incorporate this?
>> Well, that that's that's what I would
like that's kind of what motivated all
of it. as I I mentioned at the end about
glasses which would be exactly that
system
>> and it's not yeah not not really at
equilibrium and that that's what makes
it interesting right because this
evolution the longivan equation
evolution especially with the dynamic
orders is tracing a path through phase
space
and this is introducing constraints on
that paths so I'm wondering ex that is
what what I'd like to know is is does
the landscape the energy landscape
uh can is this a way of studying it?
>> Uh what role does it play?
>> Yeah. Yes. So that's uh basically if you
have several local minimar and those
switches it it may be quite interesting
for computation. So if they are those
kinetic barriers are too high then you
are too stable. it will be not uh
possible and and if it's too low it's
also unstable for this kind of things.
And uh uh another thing that would be
also interesting to see how you can uh
do for this non-equilibrium systems
with which are not based on this
relaxation of this
but maybe going towards
um non so I don't know if it's
interesting to explore this direction
it's completely non-equilibrium
like we take glasses and
jump.
>> Yeah, that's exactly what I would like
to to do. So far, I haven't I mean, one
of the reasons I chose a spin ice as a
model system is you you can engineer
uh the landscape to some extent.
Um
>> yes,
>> you can have multiple multiple energy
states. And I have I've explored it
numerically primarily uh trying to see
the consequences.
I found some oddities,
some things are but I haven't haven't
found I haven't made sense of it yet
honestly.
>> And have you tried it to
this system is a a small uh size. So
this is you can have a a very big number
of of those particles or those spins and
these big numbers may lead to some
different uh scale so that you can do
not only just explore at minimum but you
can maybe use it as a on something
completely different scale. So if you if
you have access to such a big number of
uh interacting
particles so you have like like an
avagadro
system and may lead to some new
phenomena
>> I wonder that too I mean computationally
right it starts to become very difficult
um and uh we we're we're kind of moving
in that direction trying to to be able
to treat larger systems. Uh but it it is
it starts to become very demanding
>> uh for what to control it or
>> uh to calc to simulate it
>> over sufficiently long time scales.
Yeah.
>> But if you leave it to evolve by itself.
So you because you want always like
external control what you what it does.
Yes. But if you just do it by itself
just to self revolve.
>> I said I'm not Yeah, I'm not sure I'm
following. Uh how would you what would
you look at? How would you set up that
problem?
>> Uh so for example, you may have you
measure the properties for
exampleization susceptibility of the
whole system. So this is the
>> but you don't provide the program what
you what what it should calculate but it
it systemic self organized into some
states by itself
uh let's see
so for example
I played around a little bit with this
idea
Um if I have
I mean instead of a large system maybe I
have many
smaller systems
which I run simultaneously on the same
problem but I let each one follow its
own path.
And so for example, I think I was
playing this when I showed you an
example of the tracking where I'm um
using a active inference to adjust my
parameters to optimize parameters for
the tracking.
Um, if I have several systems
simultaneously doing this and letting
them adjust their own parameters, so to
speak, then I have uh uh I think I was
trying to think about which one of one
of them is going to give me uh uh a
state which is the one I want to feed
back to my process because I can't feed
back all of so I've got 2,000 different
pro uh uh uh systems which are all
trying to predict an outcome but only
one of those is going to actually feed
back to my process. Uh which one do I
choose? So I I can make a create a
probability of which one maybe the one
that is closest that predicts closest to
the target value has the highest
probability.
So I could choose which system to follow
based on that probability. So I'm sort
of sampling between all my my different
uh uh uh systems. Is that sort of what
you're thinking of in a way?
>> But if you consider that interaction not
calculation in a uh in a normal way that
you provide a program or you design all
and control external control but uh the
material what you have interact with the
uh environment and adjust the
parameters. So without uh even writing
this uh instructions
I I'll ask a question from the live chat
or I I I think I hear you on that
Vladimir. I'm imagining one scenario
where just stimuli are presented to a
material and it could just be like sound
vibrating sand and the sand pile never
or maybe it's like an ultimate
unsupervised learning but how much of
this is the
design for
situation specific
topologies
like circuit design like and it's is it
more like an ASIC
And it's more restricted to a certain
kind of inference or how how do you
think about what functions
it can perform?
Or is it a general computer like a
processor
even if you could only do it very
slowly?
Like you play Game of Life, that kind of
stuff.
If it's just like a smaller hard drive
with a spatialization element
I maybe this is relevant I'm not sure
there's this this thesis by millage um
in this chapter he he did an image
learning it was like learning u the
emnest
digits
But he also had an interesting comment
about uh hallucinating.
If he gave it a partial or
[Music]
really a minimal amount of input, the
system came back and filled in missing
gaps in a a way which was a bit
surprising.
So, it was was like the system was was
self-organizing into a response to
something it couldn't categorize very
well. I thought that was intriguing. I
didn't really know what
what that was saying, but it seemed
interesting.
Yeah, that that makes me think of a free
energy minimum being possibly a local or
global minima but still being very far
off from like a
some other some other measure.
You know
another one example which I I don't
understand but I I I found very
interesting. There were these papers few
papers by by Fristen on uh a duet for
one if I don't know if you know these
papers with uh it was about bird song
and I I think in one of them if I
remember correctly yeah it was it was
almost as if there was one system uh
uh but then it was modeling it as if it
were also two systems. So we have one
which is singing and then it stops and
the other one picked up the song
uh and reproduced a lot of it. That that
almost seems a little like that as well.
It's kind of in that category. It's
learned it. It's following it, but it's
responding then because it it's it's
it's up in this higher layers and comes
back down.
>> I'll ask a question from live chat.
Burnt wrote, "I did not understand the
step from the predictive processing
feedback loop to active inference. Can
you explain how to add in action? What
are the affordances?"
>> This one I think. Um
so
what I have in this case do I have all
the equations? Um so there there are two
streams of input to the nanomagnets. One
is the temperature and one is the rate
of change of the temperature.
uh when you adjust a parameter
and the
parameter this x is essentially the the
rate of change of the perception with
respect to whatever value of a is in in
terms of the magnets. So it's adjusting
a in a way that is proportional to this
turns out to be an error term uh on on
uh the prediction and what is measured
and then this coefficient just measures
the the response essentially
uh that this system is going to to react
with.
Uh so
it's I've got a I've got a a single
layer and then there's the system down
here which is providing information. So
it's a feed feed forward but then this
is a feedback is what the A value is. So
it's trying to minimize a discrepancy
between the the belief and the
perception by adjusting some parameter X
and all it knows is it changes this
parameter X and there's a response uh uh
that leads to a new response from the
process. So if it changes it it gets
worse then it the signs on that term
change and so it pushes it in the other
direction.
I don't know if that does that answer
the question. So you mentioned the
frustration and the study of
frustration. So it's kind of like
there's one alignment where it's a
minimum a global or local minima
which can be designed to be a or modeled
as a convex optimization at least
locally.
And then that the system could be like
the magnet is pointing north and the
compass is aligned. And so then that's a
static state or the magnetic field could
be rotating or there could be other
forces on the compass needle. And then
the overall like tension or frustration
is basically like the the
relative malf.
So that's the downhill tension reducing
force.
>> Mhm. that at least locally the the
compass is going to reduce its the
gradient is going to go one way or it's
exactly at a flat point and then it just
is static unless there's some other
output and then to the physical part. So
then maybe to end the bird's question
about what the affordances are in the
lab, what kinds of physical measurements
and interventions can you do?
>> Well, for the magnetic system, the kind
of measurement you would do is
measure the magnetization.
Uh simple way to do that is uh if you've
got a coil of wire and you move the
magnet by it uh the field which passes
through the wire induces a current and
that can be measured. So that that
that's sort of the basis. There's other
ways to measure magnetization but that
that's kind of a simple straightforward
one. Is that that you mean the mechanics
of measure of measuring the magnetic
particles or is this a different
question?
Yeah. Just what do what do the
measurements look like? Is it um is it
and then what what can you can you make
you change the fields with spatial and
temporal precision just
>> yeah those are there's different
techniques and different technologies
are even being developed as we speak but
the maybe the simplest way to visualize
them that they're typically some sort of
variant of these kind of taper recorders
which um here you've got a coil creates
a field and that generates a particular
magnetic order just like what you've
just described or you have some way of
maybe it's another coil or there's
various devices which will are sensitive
to magnetic fields and uh you move that
device over a region of magnet and it
measures that as well can done sometimes
optically. For example, some of the
I think I pointed out the neuromorphic
that's the same problem in in these uh
reservoir computing schemes. They
actually use a combination of microwaves
and uh there there's also scanning probe
techniques to look locally and globally
at at uh the configuration of the spins.
So that there are there's a whole myriad
of different different ways that depend
very much on the system and the
materials involved.
Where do you see it being used? Is it
like a research element or a data center
piece or is it something that would be
functional in a phone or something in a
house?
uh well if in one of the one of the
ideas the motivation behind this is to
try and find uh applications of
materials that are much more efficient
than transistors in cos technologies.
So
there are different avenues you can
pursue. One of them is just pure
stochastic probabilistic
generation because it it takes fair
amount of resources to generate a random
number or pseudo random number but you
can do that with a magnetic system um
quite readily and very good at that. Uh
so people are also developing that as a
technique and that's for also
applications to probabilistic computing.
Um and there may be many applications
that that if you can make it portable
enough you could do on your phone or um
data centers for different machine
learning algorithms for compression like
image compression or I don't know about
the I don't know that much about machine
learning but I guess language models and
transformers
uh where uh it's
I I do believe I read a white paper from
the group uh where they were arguing
that maybe active inference could also
uh go and find application in those
directions as well. So it's active
inference as opposed to attention.
Um but I think that's fairly recent. So
I don't know if that's
what direction or what exactly is meant
by that.
Vladimir, do you want to ask another
question?
>> No, I think it's was quite clear.
This is I think it is a very interesting
study and uh it in the materials it is
not
uh yet this direction is very new. I
think it's not yet very how to calcute
with matter. It's a quite new direction
and that's one of the examples how it
can be realized experimentally because
in many
discussions in the publication it there
is a lot of theoretical concepts for
example this active inference and other
theoretical concepts how it should be
done and how it can be realized but
experimentally it very few uh examples
which are really implemented and this is
one of those examples.
>> I think this is a strength. This is of
this approach. This is a demonstration
among the first. I think this
>> Well, I I have a question for you also,
Vladimir, if that's all right. I mean,
>> yes. I I think you work with you I think
I saw through some of your publications
some work with nano particles and and do
you work with uh materials that have
some sort of polarization or something
analogous to
>> uh there was mostly inter field yes also
it's a one of the direction that's also
how to go to the equilibrium and in and
how to minimize the free energy in
general. So this is about for example
for interaction with the membranes and
biological systems there is also quite a
big study. So this in goes in this
direction and now what we're building
the network for materials intelligent
materials.
>> Mhm. And uh here what's uh in one of the
direction what we were trying to do is
uh uh to build the discovery engine and
also with Danielle it's in involved in
this how to also for this field of
materials how to find concepts for
example how to make
uh the
materials intelligent and what are the
uh phenomen monological concepts. So on
a very uh high level so what do you need
a memory you need uh uh computation you
need uh what is the time scales although
the system should change and what are
short what is the short term what is the
long term and this depends on the
relaxation time so kind of this because
it doesn't matter what is the system but
you can already see if uh how It can
behave because this as you see this is
based on thermal energy minimization of
the energy and there are very
fundamental concepts which are driving
driven them and the realization it's
already can be
captured from one system to another
system and you can even map it for
example and see this is you also your
system of magnets what you see it's
quite general the mechanism is quite
general can be applied to another
system. So this basically the idea of
this uh um work is how to make those
connections between different fields or
different materials.
>> And if you and the major problem there
is that you don't have reliable
experimental systems which are
demonstrating it because there is a lot
of theoretical concepts how it can be
done. uh but uh you need to have this
demonstrable fifiable
results and this is I think this is how
you show it. It can be used for another
systems.
This is kind of it can
>> thanks I'll add like one kind of
connection there that arising from your
talk is how do we think about the
aspects or the capacities or or
reliability what to even measure how to
have a a useful engineering and in
silicico and in material flexible so
that you can study different
approximations and more um fieldlike
models and more pointlike models so that
you can do normal statistics on it and
kind of port or have a good assembly
language type connection kind of between
like pro like like the analogy between
processor instructions
and that digital compute. So then it's
like well what is the approach to map
different materials and systems to their
functions and then that's where these
cognitive ontologies
like precision, attention, belief,
updating learning, all of those kinds of
of cognitive onlogical terms
become mappable from materials
where with with that sort of uh team and
work it is interesting to to look at the
method sections
and look at the parameter spaces of
where methods have or haven't been done
like which grid sizes have been done.
It's just a really highdimensional space
but possibly could be navigated uh
interestingly
to understand where where there might be
where is something like a material that
emulates a given function.
Where is that? Like what is the status
of being able to make that and then
understand that within a structured
parameterized experimental space to
prioritize
different experiments
and uh perform meta analysis to
understand how like just all all these
different pieces.
So yeah, what if Yeah, just to add a
little from what I've seen from that
project and where this sort of talk
takes me.
>> H well, I think I would be very excited
if someone would actually try to to test
this in one form or another this idea. I
I think yes, you could maybe I I chose
magnets just because I'm familiar with
them, but uh I mean other platforms
might be easier technically to implement
some example. I think the P controller
is a nice one because it's close to an
application. Uh it's used in an enormous
number of things
uh from industrial control to cruise
control on your car for example. or just
a thermostat for your home. I mean, some
practical device demonstration might be
motivational in a sense. Uh, magnets may
not be the best way to do it. Maybe
there are other systems where you could
envision uh something analogous liquid
crystals or uh something which has a has
a non-trivial response in ordering and
yet subject to to thermal processes.
uh I'm I know that even even in u
uh some convent the memory technology
for example is something which over 10
or 15 years has developed slowly but
it's in kind of in that direction a
material platform
uh where where you have have something
which has a trans transition function
which would play the role say of a like
the f function for example
uh people do look in that direction as
well. And the economics is the motivator
there is to try to find uh more power
efficient
uh
replacements for what one does with
transistors.
But I mean in trying to find
implications for something like
predictive coding, you got lots of
examples from nature. Um you can make
devices that could do something similar.
Is there a software toolkit or a a
production
possibility like how would we what what
are what kind of modeling
can others engage with from this work or
or production of of these objects
>> uh experimentally? Uh
I'm not sure I follow that like are they
synthesizable by
>> yes
>> you or how do they get synthesized or
designed or what open source or
technical documentation exists to design
the insilicone models
or or or to make them physically.
Well, I mean mainlessly
in my experience anyway if you have an
idea and something to that could be
measured is to convince someone who has
the laboratory able to do it to invest a
few years of their time and graduate
students into making it happen. Um and
so that that's a little bit what I tried
to do with this paper is demonstrate
that yeah there would be a possibility
of making these things using existing
technologies.
uh it could be done and someone may try
it. Um but that would be just one
example out of I think a new big
possibilities
uh big pro possibility space
great ideas of other systems which might
be easier to realize
but I think in this one that's one of
the reasons I chose it for this we have
laboratories here can make nano
particles and they do study uh spin
glasses so we may may be able to do
something in that direction.
Yeah, it's very fascinating. Connor
Hines and others have worked on the
spin glass system a little bit as well.
And so finding
that that that sort of a a
isomorphism between a generative model
which can be emulated with distributions
and maybe on batch data that works that
works fine but then being able to have
those
calculations which it's very small set
of them possibly or or even just one
like gradient minimization methods
alone.
and have aspects of that computation.
Just like sometimes we amortize from the
matrix to the neural network
and then go one layer into basically
offsourcing some of what appears to be
the signal processing and action
selection like features of systems and
and have that based upon the materials
properties
and then then co-design. Well, then what
symbolic
aspects
complement the materials properties
that might handle what otherwise seems
to be variance that needs to be soaked
up by an algorithm
within just like the big data processing
framework.
I think this the spin glass I think you
you mentioned the paper on spin glasses
and active inference was hints I think
it was yeah that's that's an interesting
one because one wonders is is there a
way of approaching that sort of a
problem from a different perspective uh
which is less coming up with a device or
an algorithm but it's just a way of
thinking about things which I I do
wonder about maybe maybe a direction to
look would be in active systems which is
uh I think becoming
I mentioned this paper about bird
flocking years and years ago but that
that kept up uh and I think the modern
name for this is active systems uh falls
under that rubric probably where you
think about um particles which have
almost like an attached motor and then
how do they what's the hydrodnamics of
such a system but I do wonder then uh if
this is this way of thinking way of
modeling
wouldn't be quite a natural approach in
some aspects of that kind of a of a more
complex system.
Uh to the question for me though is how
to use this analysis in a way which is
illuminating.
Um I'm not sure I know yet. I mean I did
get some insight in the exercise here. I
didn't mention it. I didn't talk about
it. But um
I found it useful to take these
equations
that govern this this uh p
it's a set of um three longitudin
coupled equations and if I look at it
from uh physics point of view as a set
of equations which are not stochastic
but let's suppose we just take those
differential equations and study their
spectral response
then
uh if I by choosing my a function
as simply as possible. One can show that
the system of equations is oscilly with
an exponential decay. And that's not
very surprising. It's just an
oscillating system that responds in a in
a well- definfined way. What is
surprising is that it it will go
asmtoically toward the target whatever
you set the target at. But when you
introduce uh uh uh noise into the
system, it finds it much more quickly.
And that that helped me understand how
these equations are working. It's it's
it's they're not mysterious. U they're
just a mechanical response, if you will.
But it's introducing the noise which
actually makes it work better and
faster.
uh that that surprised me.
So that that was maybe an insight I can
take uh to be looking at other systems
which are relaxation dynamics uh which
are non-trivial.
Um the noise matters quite a lot the
magnitude and how it's introduced
that is interesting.
Um so that that's a direction I wonder
about and the same with your question
Vladimir about a system that might have
a rather complex landscape.
I think that's interesting as well uh in
terms of how that evolves on a longer
time scale.
Um
>> yeah and this is also related for
example if you you example with the
noise uh uh the stability of those
systems because uh it is possible to
design theoretically some system but
experimentally it will not be stable and
this is the major problem that how to
control it that it will not fall apart.
This is a h that noise may destroy the
this uh the the properties this and how
do you u control it?
>> Yeah.
>> But you you showed that above a certain
temperature the functions of noise or
temperature variance of of one kind or
another it's just there's the right
amount. So that's conveniently framed as
precision or cognitive attention. And
then I think the biggest theoretical
mapping is that there's no interpolation
of a reward secondary function.
You're able to directly have a physical
analogy at least where the analytic form
of the free energy functional in silicon
can be designed to reflect what was
already transferred from the physics or
inspired from the thermo and the
information.
So the theory theory mapping to the
materials like Vladimir pointed out is
really an exciting edge that your work
is pushing along.
So it's awesome to see.
Yeah,
>> there is a a certain range of parameters
when the system is
behaving like it can compute and it it
is stable and can behave but those
parameters are not obvious how to find
this window of all these parameters
temperatures and uh all the distances
and everything what you have uh these
control parameters they should be in a
narrow range that it has sense and this
is very difficult to find
>> and that kind of connects to the active
inference for active inference that you
talked about like intelligent selection
of materials properties.
So thank you again for the work and for
sharing. hope that people are interested
and learn more and you and your
colleagues are welcome to to share more.
>> Well, thank you very much. It was it was
nice to to learn about the uh the work
that you're doing and the discussion.
So,
>> thank you.
>> Thank you.